{
  "reference_number": "10287",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "The process needs to include endorsement from all major political parties, there cant be a risk that it is repealed or fundamentally\n altered by successive governments"
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "In the short term, there is massive potential to reduce GHG through carbon offsets and potentially through changes to carbon\n accounting around wood products, this should buy us time to solve our major problems around agricultural emissions"
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions (including from new forest planting) and using some emissions reductions from overseas (international carbon units) that have strong environmental safeguards",
      "answer_index": 2,
      "notes": "\"strong environmental safeguards\" is key! there cant be any question marks of the legitimacy of imported units"
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "There should always be scope for change but this should be very narrow. It cant be for \"economic\" reasons as this is too easily\n\n manipulated to mean, short term financial benefits."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - each incoming Government should have the option to review the third budget in the sequence",
      "answer_index": 14,
      "notes": "Any changes should be able to be made, but must be done with the consensus of the major parties, not simply a parliamentary\n majority"
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Any changes should be able to be made, but must be done with the consensus of the major parties, not simply a parliamentary\n\nmajority"
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, although under economic needs to be defined to ensure that long term economic impacts are considered as well as\n\nexternalities like environmental impacts. Often economic considerations are very narrow and only focus on profitability of business or\nthe impact on household budgets. We should also consider the potential for carbon leakage, we shouldn't be taking action to reduce\n\nemissions domestically if it will cause production to shift to less efficient producers and a net increase in emissions."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "There needs to be consensus across parliament to ensure that the bill and its targets are enduring. Economic analysis of the costs\nof action generally doesn't take into account the productivity gains we will experience from shifting to a low emissions economy. Yes\n\nwe have high per capita emissions due to agriculture, but we also have high emissions because we don't invest efficiently. Despite\nhaving a highly urbanised population we under-invest in public transport and active modes making transport inefficient, we have very\n\npoor housing stock leading to poor health outcomes and housing and building stock that is expensive to heat and maintain. We have\nno standards on fuel economy for vehicles, an inefficient fleet and air pollution problems in Auckland as a result. Imagine the upside in\n\nour own well being is carbon is a driver to once and for all change all of the above - the impacts of this are not calculated in any\neconomic analysis skew the GDP impacts."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Makes decisions itself in respect of the number of units available in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 10,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "You have elected to withhold your personal details from publication."
    }
  ]
}
